Contact

+41 762248445 (Mobile) janaka2@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ janakapremathilaka (LinkedIn) javawithme.wordpress.com/ (Blog) janaka2.github.io/resume/ (Other) github.com/Janaka2 (Other)

Top Skills

Specifications

Presentations

User Experience (UX)

Languages

English (Full Professional)

Dutch (Limited Working)

French (Elementary)

German (Elementary)

Sinhalese (Native or Bilingual)

Certifications

ChatGPT: Complete ChatGPT Course For Work 2023 (Ethically)

Life Mastery - Happiness, Health & Success

Spring Certified Professional 2024 (In progress)

Mental Health First Aid Skills

Goal Setting at Work: Plan for Success and Reach Your Goals

Janaka Premathilaka

Senior Software Engineering Lead , Tech Career Mentor & Al Solutions Architect

Zug, Zug, Switzerland

Summary

For over two decades, I've been driven by two passions: solving complex technical challenges and empowering the people behind the technology. I believe the best software is built by teams who are inspired, mentored, and aligned.

My principle is simple: find a way or make one. I believe the most complex challenges have clear, efficient solutions, and it's this mindset that has driven me to deliver resilient, high-volume platforms and modernize legacy systems for clients like UBS and the European Commission. I take full ownership of outcomes, proactively addressing issues before they become roadblocks to ensure smooth, successful project delivery. While my expertise is grounded in enterprise technologies like Java/Spring Boot and Kubernetes, I am fluent in the new stack. I build practical, measurable AI solutions from custom agents to optimizing RAGs for production. I don't just talk about AI; I ship it.

I'm always open to connecting with fellow technology leaders and aspiring engineers. Whether you're looking to scale your engineering team or navigate your own career path, feel free to send a connection request. Let's discuss how we can build the future of tech, together.

Experience

UBS

Sr. Full-Stack Solution Engineer at UBS and Cognizant January 2024 - Present (1 year 10 months)

Greater Zurich Area

Experimented with running local LLMs (e.g. Llama 3) and fine-tuned inference pipelines for task-specific automations.

Credit Suisse

Sr. Full-Stack Solution Engineer at Credit Suisse and Cognizant May 2019 - January 2024 (4 years 9 months)

Zurich, Switzerland

Position: IT Solution Developer at CS

Responsibilities:

Design, implement, and maintain high-volume and low-latency Java applications necessary for mission-critical systems.

Ensure the high availability and performance of applications.

Participate in all phases of the development lifecycle.

Write well-designed, efficient, and testable code.

Conduct software analysis, programming, testing, and debugging.

Manage Java and Java EE application development.

Confirm designs comply with specifications.

Prepare and produce releases of software components.

Transform requirements into stipulations.

Support continuous improvement through investigating alternatives and technologies.

Present designs for architectural review.

Projects:

GBSS MDM:

Developed a high-performance, responsive Master Data Management Tool from scratch, with ongoing enhancements.

DSL:

Developed a web application for building dynamic consumer endpoints for a big data platform.

Designed Java backend for a high-volume FX trading platform, automating & enhancing efficiency. Applied FIX protocol knowledge to streamline trades, boosting system responsiveness by 20%, & improving execution times.

Case Managements:

Developed multiple case management tools from scratch and implemented major enhancements.

Enhanced due diligence-related case management.

Managed high-risk-related case management.

Implemented common case management functionalities.

Integrated multiple case managements with streaming for optimized highvolume data search and data lake analysis.

Automated case creations with scheduled pickups.

Cash & Card Management:

Renovated the application and integrated hardware with the web application.

Technologies & Tools:

ReactJs, Java 11-17, Groovy, Spring5, Spring Boot MVC, REST, Spring Data, Maven, Git, Oracle, PL/SQL, H2 DB, IntelliJ, WebLogic, Apache POI, GraphQL, Apache Kafka, Liquibase.

DevOps & Project Management:

GitOps, OpenShift, Kubernetes, Docker, Splunk, Grafana, Helm, Jenkins, Cl/CD, JIRA, Scrum.

UBS

Sr. Software Developer at UBS and Cognizant January 2018 - May 2019 (1 year 5 months) Zürich Area, Switzerland

Role: IT Solution Development Specialist for Banking Products and Services

Key Responsibilities:

Upgrading and modernizing over 20 software components using the latest technologies such as Java 8, Apache Camel, Spring, and Hibernate, OAS, Swagger.

Packaging software for deployment on Linux servers and ensuring seamless operation.

Implementing trigger-based pipeline jobs through Jenkins automation.

Delivering both front-end and back-end development and maintenance work.

Developing RESTful web services to meet business needs.

Improving and maintaining unit and integration test coverage to ensure software quality.

Automating testing through Cucumber BDD and improving the overall testing process.

Developing fully dynamic React user interfaces using JSON schema.

Updating and reorganizing existing applications to meet the latest technical requirements.

Migrating the software codebase from SVN to GIT and setting up Jenkins jobs.

Automating the delivery pipeline through Jenkins for static code analysis,

remote upload, and custom report/email generation.

Overseeing all aspects of software release activities.

Participating in sprint planning and estimating technical tasks.

European Commission

6 years 8 months

Sr. Full-Stack Java/JEE Developer at European Commission's DIGIT Division

February 2016 - January 2018 (2 years)

Brussels Area, Belgium

Key Responsibilities:

Providing functional and technical support for the e-procurement system. Accurately estimating technical tasks.

Developing front-end and back-end applications to meet a wide range of technical and functional requirements.

And develop microservices and integrate them utilizing enterprise integration patterns, specifically leveraging Spring Integration for message routing, transformation, aggregation, and synchronization.

Enhancing code quality through unit and integration testing.

Implementing JBPM workflows for various business processes.

Providing maintenance and L3 support for applications.

Managing software releases using Jasper & Jenkins jobs.

Technologies Used:

Java/J2EE, Adobe Flex, Angular 2-4, Bootstrap, jQuery, KendoUI, Spring/ Hibernate, Spring MVC, EJB3, Oracle, SVN, GIT, JBoss JBPM, UML, SOA, Eclipse, Mockito, WebLogic, Action Script, RequireJS, DHTML, CSS & SASS, XML, XSLT, XSD, JIRA, Scrum, etc.

Sr. Java/JEE Developer Specializing in E-Procurement Solutions March 2014 - February 2016 (2 years)

DIGIT

Expert Java/J2EE Web Application Development

Sr. Java/JEE Developer Specializing in E-Procurement Solutions June 2011 - March 2014 (2 years 10 months)

Expert Java/JEE Web Application Development

Simbios(Client: Centric IT Solutions)

Java/JEE Developer Specializing in POS Terminal Software and Sales February 2011 - June 2011 (5 months)

Java/JEE Specialist Consultant

Key Responsibilities:

Planning and estimating technical tasks in a Scrum environment.

Implementing planned solutions.

Increasing code quality through unit and integration testing.

Providing maintenance and resolving bugs.

Technologies Used:

Java/J2EE, Java Swing, Spring/Hibernate, SVN, Eclipse, Junit4, Mockito, Oracle, UML, JIRA, Scrum, etc.

Simbios(Client: J&J, Cronos)

Java/JEE Developer Specializing in Healthcare and Well-being Solutions

July 2010 - January 2011 (7 months)

Senior Java/JEE Consultant at Johnson & Johnson

Role: Java/JEE Specialist Consultant in the Hospital and Health Care domain.

Key Responsibilities:

Contributing to solution design.

Implementing both front-end and back-end solutions.

Writing Junit tests.

Conducting end-to-end testing.

Resolving bugs and providing maintenance.

Methodology: Scrum

Key Technologies:

JEE, JDK1.5, Spring 2.5, Spring MVC, Hibernate, Oracle DB, DWR, JQuery, TortoiseSVN, Eclipse IDE, Display tag library 1.2, Maven, Tomcat for development, WebLogic in production, etc.

Simbios(Client : Nokia Siemens Networks, Devoteam, USG)
Java/JEE Developer Specializing in Multimedia Telecommunications
August 2009 - July 2010 (1 year)

Senior Java/JEE Specialist Consultant in Telecommunications Key Responsibilities:

Providing functional analysis support.

Collaborating on solution design.

Implementing end-to-end multimedia telecommunications solutions.

Integrating Arris Next Generation video server with XML over HTTP & JAXB.

Implementing closed captioning and subtitling with the CMS.

Web browser-controlled PVR integration with HTTP Capture server.

XML RPC Client/Server call back implementation for PVR.

Conducting comprehensive testing with JUnit and Mockito.

Methodology: Spiral

Key Technologies: Java/JEE, EJB2, Hibernate3, Oracle, HSQLDB, JBPM, XDoclet, ANT, Eclipse, Struts, SOAP, JAXB, JAXRPC, JAX-WS, XML, XSD, JBOSS, JSTL, SSL, X509 certificate, Java key store, Apache XML-RPC, Mockito testing, etc.

Simbios(Client: Van Genechten Packaging)
Senior Java/JEE Developer for Products and Services
January 2009 - July 2010 (1 year 7 months)

Role: Senior Java/JEE Specialist Consultant in the Packaging and Containers (CMS) domain

Responsibilities:

Design, development, and implementation of solutions in the Packaging and Containers industry.

Extensive testing to ensure the quality and stability of the software.

Troubleshooting and fixing bugs as needed.

Methodology: Scrum

Technologies Utilized: Java Enterprise Edition (JEE) platform, BEA WebLogic, Swing Widget Toolkit, Hibernate3, Java Persistence API (JPA), Enterprise JavaBeans (EJB2), MySQL, Oracle, Perforce Repository, BlazeDS (Java remoting with Adobe Flex 3), Spring 2.0.8, Apache Tomcat 6, Apache IVY for dependency management, Concurrent Versions System (CVS), Cruise Control, JUnit, Simple Object Access Protocol (SOAP), Web Services Description Language (WSDL), Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP), etc.

Roomsnet.com

Java/JEE Developer & Technical Lead in the Hotel Reservation Domain March 2007 - October 2008 (1 year 8 months)

Tech Lead and Senior Java/JEE Developer in the Leisure, Travel, and Tourism Domain

Responsibilities:

Design and development of custom solutions to meet the unique business requirements of the Roomsnet niche market.

Optimizing code for improved performance and scalability.

Keeping up with the latest advancements in Java/JEE technologies to ensure high profitability and efficiency.

Implementing the Scrum methodology to streamline product development. Technologies Used:

Java/JEE Platform: Java Server Faces Framework, Enterprise Java Beans 3, JBoss Seam (combining EJB3 and JSF), Hibernate 3 Java Persistence, Oracle, JBoss Application Server.

JavaScript (AJAX with JBoss Seam remoting), XML/XSLT, PHP5, Apache, Apache Load Balancing, Elasticsearch, MySQL, HTML/DHTML, XHTML, CSS for client-side web pages and query pages.

PHP-Java Bridge implementation, Linux, etc.

ABSI.BE

Java/JEE Developer in the Healthcare Industry May 2006 - March 2007 (11 months)

Role: Java/JEE Developer in the Information Technology and Services Domain Responsibilities:

Implementation of significant improvements to a B2B application for www.komatsu.com

Development of a new internal project management module for B2B integration

Adaptation of Salesforce.com applications

Technologies Used:

Java/JEE Platform, Spring Framework, Hibernate 3 Java Persistence, Apache Tomcat 6 Container, MySQL, Adobe Flex Rich Client Web Interfaces, JavaScript with AJAX (DOJO/DWR), SOAP, Spring SOA Implementation, Apache Struts, MVC, XML/XSLT, etc.

Union bank Of Colombo Ltd

Senior Software Engineer in Java/JEE technologies in the Banking and Finance Industry

May 2004 - May 2006 (2 years 1 month)

Colombo, Western Province, Sri Lanka

As a Software Engineer in the Private Banking domain, my responsibilities include analyzing business requirements with a focus on the core banking application, the UBC loan system, the UBC lease schedule generating system, and the cheques and passbook printing system. I collaborate with my team to design effective solutions, implement these solutions and enhance them through thorough testing. I also provide maintenance and installation support to remote branches. The technologies I use include EJB2, JSP, Servlets 2.2, Postgres DB and DB2 on AS400, Apache Tomcat5, and JT400 for accessing the OS/400/DB2 environment, among others.

University of Sri Jayewardenepura
Computer Science & Statistics Instructor.
February 2004 - May 2004 (4 months)
Sri Jayawardenepura Kotte, Western Province, Sri Lanka

Computer Science and Statistics Instructor with a passion for education and empowering students with essential knowledge and skills.

Education

University of Sri Jayewardenepura

BSc, Computer Science, Statistics, Mathematics · (1999 - 2003)

Sun Java SCJP,SCBCD,SCEA1,SCWCD(69), Java and JEE technologies · (2005 - 2006)

University of Colombo
Unix/Linux Fundamentals,Networks & Systems Administration, Unix/Linux · (2005 - 2005)

Australian computer society
ACS Examinataions in IT, IT · (2002 - 2002)